<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Climbing on A Man, a Van, and a Plan</title>
    <link>http://blog.marrama.com/tags/climbing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Climbing on A Man, a Van, and a Plan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 11:59:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.marrama.com/tags/climbing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Regular Route on Fairview Dome</title>
      <link>http://blog.marrama.com/post/regular_route_fairview/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 11:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.marrama.com/post/regular_route_fairview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My day began on a bright and sunny morning in Tuolumne meadows without a
partner. I had prevoiusly arranged to spend the day climbing with a user on
mountain project, but when I met him he was on his way out to do laundry in Lee
Vining. This was undesirable yet understandable, given he was living and
climbing in the meadows for 2 months. Upon hearing this, I started scanning the
Tuolumne Meadows general store parking lot for other potential partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about a half hour sitting in the back of my van reading a book with my
climbing gear visible, I spied a potential candidate. Approach shoes? Check.
Nice bed in the back of his car? Check. Build of a climber? Check. He also had
a settlers of catan bumper sticker, an unambiguous sign of good taste. His name
was Jack, and to no one&amp;rsquo;s surprise, he was also up in the meadows on a climbing
trip. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t find his friends he was supposed to do Matthes Crest with, so
we didn&amp;rsquo;t waste any time taking off to go climb somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first objective was West Crack on Daff dome, which is a classic 5.8 route that
ascends a splitter crack up the side of the dome over 4 pitches. After the
first pitch it was clear Jack was a great partner. We worked very well
together, climbed around the same level (Jack was clearly the superior
climber), and were both stoked to climb all day. We made quick work of West
Crack, and afterwards wanted something a little more substantial. Staring us in
the face was Fairview dome, and what better route to attempt than the most
famous one leading directly up its prow? When I mentioned that the regular
route was in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fifty_Classic_Climbs_of_North_America&#34;&gt;famous list of 50 classic
climbs&lt;/a&gt;,
Jack got especially psyched to give it a go. It was 1pm, there were no clouds
in the sky, no chance of thunderstorms, and we were ready to send.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got to the base of the climb around 2 or so. I took the first pitch, which
is the crux of the whole climb. It started with 75 feet of easy climbing, then
as the dome curved up it got steadily harder, until the crux about 150 feet up
which is a slippery 5.9 fingercrack in a corner. I put in a prolific amount of
pro and managed to make it clean to the belay. We had a 70 meter rope, which
allowed me to make it to a spacious ledge with a tree to anchor to. I highly
recommend getting to this ledge any way possible to end the first
pitch, even if you have to simulclimb on a 60 meter. All of the other belay
spots below are marginal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4792.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking down on the first pitch. The crux was right below the bright part of
the crack&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We swung leads the whole climb, so Jack took pitch 2 while I enjoyed the
view. The majority of pitch 2 was an awesome flaring hand crack. It was rated
5.8, but it was surprisingly sustained. I was starting to get a little
fatigued, but the climbing was just moderate enough and too damn fun to get
tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4790.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking up pitch 2. The rope disappears up the corner and the pitch eventually
makes its way to a ledge on the left&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third pitch wasn&amp;rsquo;t as obvious as the first two. I ended up meandering up a
system of cracks and knobby faces to crescent ledge, a large ledged shaped like
(you guessed it!) a crescent. Despite this pitch being a &amp;ldquo;choose your own
adventure to crescent ledge&amp;rdquo; style climb, it still was quite good. Jack did a
little variation up a crack in a roof that he was quite psyched on. It should
be noted that we ended up doing 4 guidebook pitches in 3 actual pitches with a
70 meter. They were easy to link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4795.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking down on the very end of pitch 3 from the start of crescent ledge.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4797.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Great spot to eat an energy bar or 3!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a little break to devour some clif bars and let our toes rest from
hours of climbing, then started up pitch 4. This pitch was easy to forget,
mainly because it was about 120 feet of easy climbing up crescent ledge. My
feet weren&amp;rsquo;t happy to be back in climbing shoes, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4798.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Crescent ledge really is a crescent. P4 goes right up the ledge/corner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took pitch 5, which was a link-up of pitch 6 and 7 in the guidebook. The
first half of the pitch was awesome climbing. I went up a corner into a crack
system that goes straight up a roof with an old piton. The rest of the pitch
wandered up a ledge system. I eventually set a belay at the top of a smaller
ledge close to easier terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4826.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The view from the P6 belay, looking down on the second half of the pitch. Jack
is undoubtedly wondering how I managed to get so horrible at rope management.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jack lead one more easy pitch that traversed back right to the bottom of a big
stretch of 3rd and 4th class terrain. At this point the guidebook showed 5 more
pitches of extremely easy climbing with occasional 5.5 sections, so we decided
to simul-climb the rest of it. We folded the rope in half, I took all the gear,
and I set off with Jack belaying and eventually following. We made it to the
summit about 30 minutes later after walking up the majority of the last
stretch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4810.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking down on the ledges we simul-climbed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We summitted around 6:50, just in time to savor the incredible view
all around us. We walked off in the dusk and made it back to the cars around
7:50. We were both exhausted yet giddy that a non-day of climbing turned into a
worthy epic, ascending over 1600 feet and one of the best routes around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/small_IMG_4807.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking east towards the meadows. The picture doesn&amp;rsquo;t really do it justice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The East Buttress of Middle Cathedral</title>
      <link>http://blog.marrama.com/post/east_butt_middle_cathedral/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2016 11:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.marrama.com/post/east_butt_middle_cathedral/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After being introduced to climbing in the valley about a year ago, I&amp;rsquo;ve been
constantly building and refining an ordered list of Classic Climbs that I Must
Do. The east buttress of middle cathedral occupied a special spot on The List,
because it seemed like it would be both a way to push my boundaries and a
shitload of fun. According to everything I had read beforehand, the route
offered continuous 5.8 to 5.10c climbing over 11 pitches of perfect granite. I
can barely lead 5.9 trad climbs and I&amp;rsquo;ve never done more than 5 pitches of 5.8,
so this route seemed like the next logical step up. The route offers lots of
possibilities to aid through the cruxes and to bail if needed, so why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity came last week when I was in the valley with my buddy Gavin.
Gavin climbs at about the same level and has the same amount of stoke (very
high), so we went for it on a sunny day. We got to the pullout and finished
racking up at around 8:30, and thanks to a well marked climber&amp;rsquo;s trail we
got to the base of the climb around 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We swung leads the whole time, and I took the first lead linking up pitch 1 and
2. Pitch 1 was about 100 feet of reasonably easy climbing, but it quickly heats
up at the start of P2 with a 5.8 roof. The roof was a little tricky and took me some
extra time to figure out, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bad once I found a hidden jug. The
rest of the climbing to the top of P2 was fairly easy. The rope drag at the top
of P2 was &lt;em&gt;horrendous&lt;/em&gt;; I should&amp;rsquo;ve used longer slings at the roof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4306.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;View from the top of P2. Not bad!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4308.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gavin getting psyched to link P3 and P4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gavin took the next lead, which was a linkup of pitches 3 and 4. Our 60 meter
rope was just long enough to link the 2 pitches. These pitches were fantastic.
The start to P3 was a somewhat stiff 5.8 fingercrack wedged into a corner, and
the rest of the 2 pitches were super fun laybacks. The climbing was very
interesting and confidence inspiring, especially on toprope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/GOPR0023.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The start of P3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/GOPR0030.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking down on the end of P4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/GOPR0027.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Stoke level: still high&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4310.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;El Cap was staring at us the whole climb. Tempting!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next pitch was the crux pitch, and it fell on me. There are 2 options for
pitch 5: the original route, which starts with a bolt ladder that can go free
at 5.10c and then continues to a 5.9 roof, or a 5.10a face climb that continues
to a small roof and easier face climb. After debating with myself outloud, I
eventually said &lt;em&gt;fuck it&lt;/em&gt; and went for the 10a face climb option. I figured it
would be an even larger accomplishment to do the whole route free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The free variation was actually quite fun. The face climb leading up to the
roof was easier than expected, and the roof took a little bit of thought but it
wasn&amp;rsquo;t horrible. After the first bolt (which is easy to get to), the crux is
relatively easy to protect. The face climb after the roof is an incredibly fun 5.6
filled with big juggy slopers. The face gave way to a fun little layback
section, which ends the pitch at a ledge with a set of bolts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4309.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The start of P5 - very fun knobby traverse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the topo, I thought that it would be straightforward to link pitches
5 and 6 with a 60 meter rope. When I got to the anchor at the top of P5, I
decided to go for it even though the rope drag was already kind of bad. The
first half of P6 is a face climb requiring lots of balance; the rope drag
didn&amp;rsquo;t help with that. The second half was a layback up to another ledge. I
just made it onto the ledge when I heard Gavin yell out &amp;ldquo;Joe, you have 5
feet!&amp;ldquo;, and unfortunately the chains were 15 feet over to the right on the
ledge. After some back and forth, we decided to simul-climb to the P6 anchor.
Fortunately, Gavin only had to do a short easy traverse to the first bolt of P5
to give me enough slack to get to the anchors. I anchored in with a great sigh
of relief, put Gavin on belay, and ate a sandwich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/GOPR0036.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The P6 chains! Yes! I have to work on keeping my anchors neater&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/GOPR0038.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The ledge leading up to the chains. I ran it out to preserve rope and not
contribute to drag. Also it was easy :)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gavin led the next pitch (P7), which consisted of more fun layback cracks in
left-facing corners. We both made quick work of it. I took pitch 8, which was
one of the most memorable of the whole climb. The pitch started with a short
blocky section narrowing down to a wide handcrack in the back of a big flared
groove. The end of the pitch was yet another fun layback to short face
traverse. The climbing was very heady and thought-provoking; it was easy to
climb poorly with haste, but the climbing was easy when done right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4311.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The start of P7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4322.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking down at the end of P7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4326.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gavin following up the end of P8&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, fatigue was beginning to set in. We had started at a
less-than-ideal time when the route was beginning to get sun, and we had baked
in direct sunlight for the whole time. It was around 1:30 when we both got to
the top of P8 and only then were we escaping the sun. We took a little break to
recuperate and hydrate, then Gavin set off on P9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4333.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking up at P9 which goes around to the left of the bushes. Almost out of
the sun!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pitch 9 was a less memorable pitch. It followed a small crack up more left
facing corners. Pitch 10 was my last lead. The pitch started with a
surprisingly hard finger crack that was marked 5.6 on the topo, then continued
up a narrow crack system into a section of 5.8 finger crack that goes into a
gully. I was moving exceedingly slow on this bit, making sure I was using the
least amount of energy possible without getting too careless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/GOPR0059.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gavin cruising up P10. I probably should have gone up the crack directly under
me, it looked like better climbing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last pitch, pitch 11, was Gavin&amp;rsquo;s lead. The first half was a large flaring
5.7 chimney followed by some easier 4th class. The chimney was quite unwelcome
to both of us; we both had packs on and aren&amp;rsquo;t fans of chimnies. Gavin grunted
his way up, I followed in the same fashion, and we promptly collapsed at the
top-out and devoured the rest of our food and water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4335.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gavin mustering up all remaining energy to lead the chimney behind him&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/GOPR0068.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We done did it! The topout wasn&amp;rsquo;t glorious but it was more than welcome&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The descent was a little more than we bargained for. We followed the beta in
the guidebook for the Kat Walk to the best of our abilities, but we ended up
following a pseudo-trail to a series of 5 rappels with our single 60m
rope. According to &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.stanford.edu/~clint/yos/katpen.htm&#34;&gt;this topo&lt;/a&gt;,
we went down the penny pinnacle rappel route instead. We missed the last
rappel (rappel 8 in the topo), and I ended up downclimbing 10 feet in a large
chimney to flat ground, while Gavin downclimbed some dirty 3rd class. It was a
little unnerving following a route that was obviously not in our guidebook, but
fortunately it was a very well established rappel route. We spent the next 45
minutes scrambling back down the gully between higher cathedral and middle
cathedral to the car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4350.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The chimney I downclimbed. This may have been a first descent - it was covered
in dust and spiderwebs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4352.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Higher cathedral looking majestic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent almost 7 hours climbing, about 2 and a half hours on the descent, and
around 30 minutes on the approach, bringing us to a grand total of 10 hours.
While a portion of this time was definitely type 2 fun (especially the
descent), the majority of the excursion was exceedingly enjoyable. This won&amp;rsquo;t
be the last time I go up this route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://blog.marrama.com/images/IMG_4354.jpg&#34;
onmouseover=&#34;this.setAttribute(&#39;src&#39;, &#39;/images/route_overlay.jpg&#39;);&#34;
onmouseout=&#34;this.setAttribute(&#39;src&#39;, &#39;/images/IMG_4354.jpg&#39;);&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The route in retrospect, taken on the descent. Hover over the picture for what I&amp;rsquo;m fairly
certain is the route we took&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>